<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-thomson-webpush-protocol-latest">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="HTTP Web Push">
      Generic Event Delivery Using HTTP Push
    </title>

    <author initials="M." surname="Thomson" fullname="Martin Thomson">
      <organization>Mozilla</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>331 E Evelyn Street</street>
          <city>Mountain View</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94041</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>martin.thomson@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="E." surname="Damaggio" fullname="Elio Damaggio">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Microsoft Way</street>
          <city>Redmond</city>
          <region>WA</region>
          <code>98052</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>elioda@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="B." surname="Raymor" fullname="Brian Raymor">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Microsoft Way</street>
          <city>Redmond</city>
          <region>WA</region>
          <code>98052</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>brian.raymor@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2015"/>
    <area>RAI</area>
    <workgroup>WEBPUSH</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>HTTP</keyword>
    <keyword>HTTP2</keyword>
    <keyword>Push</keyword>
    <keyword>WebPush</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        A simple protocol for the delivery of realtime events to user agents is
        described.  This scheme uses HTTP/2 server push.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>
        Many applications on mobile and embedded devices require continuous
        access to network communications so that real-time events - such as
        incoming calls or messages - can be delivered (or "pushed") in a timely
        fashion. These devices typically have limited power reserves, so finding
        more efficient ways to serve application requirements greatly benefits
        the application ecosystem.
      </t>
      <t>
        One significant contributor to power usage is the radio.  Radio
        communications consume a significant portion of the energy budget
        on a wireless device.
      </t>
      <t>
        Uncoordinated use of persistent connections or sessions from multiple
        applications can contribute to unnecessary use of the device radio,
        since each independent session independently incurs overheads.  In
        particular, keep alive traffic used to ensure that middleboxes do not
        prematurely time out sessions, can result in significant waste.
        Maintenance traffic tends to dominate over the long term, since events
        are relatively rare.
      </t>
      <t>
        Consolidating all real-time events into a single session ensures more
        efficient use of network and radio resources.  A single service
        consolidates all events, distributing those events to applications as
        they arrive.  This requires just one session, avoiding duplicated
        overhead costs.
      </t>
      <t>
        The <xref target="API">W3C Web Push API</xref> describes an API that
        enables the use of a consolidated push service from web applications.
        This expands on that work by describing a protocol that can be used to:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            request the delivery of a push message to a user agent,
          </t>
          <t>
            create new push message delivery subscriptions, and
          </t>
          <t>
            monitor for new push messages.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        Requesting the delivery of events is particularly important for the Web
        Push API.  The subscription, management and monitoring functions are
        currently fulfilled by proprietary protocols; these are adequate, but do
        not offer any of the advantages that standardization affords.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document intentionally does not describe how a push service is
        discovered.  Discovery of push services is left for future efforts, if
        it turns out to be necessary at all.  User agents are expected to be
        configured with a URL for a push service.
      </t>

      <section anchor="terminology" title="Conventions and Terminology">
        <t>
          In cases where normative language needs to be emphasized, this
          document falls back on established shorthands for expressing
          interoperability requirements on implementations: the capitalized
          words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "SHOULD" and "MAY".  The meaning of these is
          described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
        </t>

        <t>
          This document defines the following terms:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="application:">
              Both the sender and ultimate consumer of push messages.  Many
              applications have components that are run on a user agent and
              other components that run on servers.
            </t>
            <t hangText="application server:">
              The component of an application that runs on a server and requests
              the delivery of a push message.
            </t>
            <t hangText="push message subscription:">
              A message delivery context that is established between the user
              agent and the push service and shared with the application server.
              All push messages are associated with a push message subscription.
            </t>
            <t hangText="push message:">
              A message sent from an application server to a user agent via a
              push service.
            </t>
            <t hangText="push message receipt:">
              A message delivery confirmation sent from the push server to the
              application server.
            </t>
            <t hangText="push service:">
              A service that delivers push messages to user agents.
            </t>
            <t hangText="user agent:">
              A device and software that is the recipient of push messages.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          Examples in this document use the <xref target="RFC7230">HTTP/1.1
          message format</xref>.  Many of the exchanges can be completed using
          HTTP/1.1, where HTTP/2 is necessary, the more verbose frame format
          from <xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-http2"/> is used.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Overview">
      <t>
        A general model for push services includes three basic actors: a user
        agent, a push service, and an application (server).
      </t>
      <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 +-------+           +--------------+       +-------------+
 |  UA   |           | Push Service |       | Application |
 +-------+           +--------------+       +-------------+
     |                      |                      |
     |      Subscribe       |                      |
     |--------------------->|                      |
     |       Monitor        |                      |
     |<====================>|                      |
     |                      |                      |
     |           Provide Subscription Write Access |
     |-------------------------------------------->|
     |                      |                      |
     :                      :                      :
     |                      |     Push Message     |
     |    Push Message      |<---------------------|
     |<---------------------|                      |
     |                      |                      |
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        At the very beginning of the process, a new  message subscription is
        created by the user agent and then distributed to its application
        server. This subscription is the basis of all future interactions between
        the actors.
      </t>
      <t>
        To offer more control for authorization, a message subscription is
        modeled as two resources with different capabilities:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            A subscription resource is used to receive messages from a
            subscription and to delete a subscription. It is private to the user
            agent.
          </t>
          <t>
            A push resource is used to send messages to a subscription. It is
            public and shared by the the user agent with its application server.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        It is expected that a unique subscription will be provided to each
        application; however, there are no inherent cardinality constraints in
        the protocol.  Multiple subscriptions might be created for the same
        application, or multiple applications could use the same subscription.
        Note however that sharing subscriptions has security and privacy
        implications.
      </t>
      <t>
        Subscriptions have a limited lifetime.  They can also be terminated by
        either the push service or user agent at any time. User agents and
        application servers must be prepared to manage changes in subscription
        state.
      </t>

      <section anchor="resources" title="HTTP Resources">
        <t>
          This protocol uses <xref target="RFC7230">HTTP resources</xref> and
          <xref target="RFC5988">link relations</xref>.  The following resources
          are defined:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="push service:">
              This resource is used to create push message subscriptions (see
              <xref target="message_subscription"/>).  A URL for the push
              service is configured into user agents.
            </t>
            <t hangText="push message subscription:">
              This resource provides read and delete access for a message
              subscription. A user agent <xref target="monitor">receives push
              messages</xref> using a push message subscription.  Every push
              message subscription has exactly one push resource associated with
              it.
            </t>
            <t hangText="push:">
              A push resource is used by the application server to request the
              delivery of a push message (see <xref target="send"/>).  A link
              relation of type "urn:ietf:params:push:message" is used to
              identify a push resource.
            </t>
            <t hangText="push message:">
              A push message resource is created to identify push messages that
              have been accepted by the push service.  The push message resource
              is also used to acknowledge receipt of a push message.
            </t>
            <t hangText="receipt subscribe:">
              A receipt subscription resource is used by applications to create
              a receipt subscription (see <xref
              target="receipt_subscription"/>).  A link relation of type
              "urn:ietf:params:push:receipt:subscribe" is used to identity a
              receipt subscribe resource.
            </t>
            <t hangText="receipt subscription:">
              An application server <xref target="request_receipt">receives
              delivery confirmations</xref> for push messages using a receipt
              subscription.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="message_subscription" title="Subscribing for Push Messages">
      <t>
        A user agent sends a POST request to its configured push service
        resource to create a new subscription.
      </t>
      <figure>
        <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
POST /subscribe/ HTTP/1.1
Host: push.example.net

]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        A response with a 201 (Created) status code MUST include a URI for a new
        push message subscription resource in the Location header field.
      </t>
      <t>
        The push server MUST provide a URI for the push resource corresponding
        to the push message subscription using a link relation of type
        "urn:ietf:params:push:message".
      </t>
      <t>
        The push server MUST provide a URI for a receipt subscribe resource in a
        link relation of type "urn:ietf:params:push:receipt:subscribe".
      </t>
      <t>
         An application-specific method is used to send the pust and receipt
         subscribe URIs to the application server.  Confidentiality protection
         and application server authentication SHOULD be used to ensure that
         these URIs are not disclosed to unauthorized recipients (see <xref
         target="authorization"/>).
      </t>
      <figure>
        <artwork type="inline">
  <![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 201 Created
Date: Thu, 11 Dec 2014 23:56:52 GMT
Link: </p/JzLQ3raZJfFBR0aqvOMsLrt54w4rJUsV>;
        rel="urn:ietf:params:push:message"
Link: </receipts/xjTG79I3VuptNWS0DsFu4ihT97aE6UQJ>;
        rel="urn:ietf:params:push:receipt:subscribe"
Location: https://push.example.net/s/LBhhw0OohO-Wl4Oi971UGsB7sdQGUibx
Cache-Control: max-age:864000, private

]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>
    <section anchor="receipt_subscription"
             title="Subscribing for Push Message Receipts">
      <t>
        An application server requests the creation of a receipt subscription by
        sending a HTTP POST request to the receipt subscribe resource learned
        from a user agent.
      </t>
      <figure>
        <artwork type="inline">
          <![CDATA[
POST /receipts/xjTG79I3VuptNWS0DsFu4ihT97aE6UQJ HTTP/1.1
Host: push.example.net

]]>
        </artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        A successful response with a 201 (Created) status code includes a URI
        for the receipt subscription resource in the Location header field.
      </t>
      <figure>
        <artwork type="inline">
          <![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 201 Created
Date: Thu, 11 Dec 2014 23:56:52 GMT
Location: https://push.example.net/r/3ZtI4YVNBnUUZhuoChl6omUvG4ZM9mpN

]]>
        </artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        A push service SHOULD provide the same receipt subscribe URI to user
        agents.  Equality of the receipt subscribe URI can be used by an
        application server as a signal that an existing receipt subscription
        resource can be reused.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="send" title="Requesting Push Message Delivery">
      <t>
        An application server requests the delivery of a push message by sending
        a HTTP request to a push resource provided by a user agent. The push
        message is included in the body of the request.
      </t>
      <figure>
        <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
POST /p/LBhhw0OohO-Wl4Oi971UGsB7sdQGUibx HTTP/1.1
Host: push.example.net
Content-Type: text/plain;charset=utf8
Content-Length: 36

iChYuI3jMzt3ir20P8r_jgRR-dSuN182x7iB
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <preamble>
          A 201 (Created) response indicates that the push message was accepted.
          A URI for the push message resource that was created in response to
          the request is included in the Location header field.  This does not
          indicate that the message was delivered to the user agent.
        </preamble>
        <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 201 Created
Date: Thu, 11 Dec 2014 23:56:55 GMT
Location: https://push.example.net/d/qDIYHNcfAIPP_5ITvURr-d6BGtYnTRnk

]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        A push service MAY generate a 413 (Payload Too Large) status code in
        response to requests that include an entity body that is too large.
        Push services MUST NOT generate a 413 status code in responses to an
        entity body that is 4k (4096 bytes) or less in size.
      </t>

      <section anchor="request_receipt" title="Requesting Push Message Receipts">
        <t>
          An application server can use the Push-Receipt header field to request
          a confirmation from the push server when a push message is delivered
          and acknowledged by the user agent. The Push-Receipt header field is a
          URI-Reference as defined in Section 2.7 of
          <xref target="RFC7230"/>.
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork type="abnf">
            <![CDATA[
Push-Receipt = URI-reference
          ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The application sets the Push-Receipt header field value to a receipt
          subscription URI.  This receipt subscription resource MUST be created
          from the same receipt subscribe resource as was included with the push
          message subscription (see <xref target="message_subscription"/>).
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ttl" title="Push Message Time-To-Live">
        <t>
          A push service can improve the reliability of push message delivery
          considerably by storing push messages for a period.  User agents are
          often only intermittently connected, and so benefit from having short
          term message storage at the push service.
        </t>
        <t>
          Delaying delivery might also be used to batch communication with the
          user agent, thereby conserving radio resources.
        </t>
        <t>
          Some push messages are not useful once a certain period of time
          elapses.  Delivery of messages after they have ceased to be relevant
          is wasteful.  For example, if the push message contains a call
          notification, receiving a message after the caller has abandoned the
          call is of no value; the application at the user agent is forced to
          suppress the message so that it does not generate a useless alert.
        </t>
        <t>
          An application server can use the TTL header field to limit the time
          that a push message is retained by a push service.  The TTL header
          field contains a value in seconds that describes how long a push
          message is retained by the push service.
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork type="abnf"><![CDATA[
TTL = 1*DIGIT
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          Once the Time-To-Live (TTL) period elapses, the push service MUST
          remove the push message and cease any attempt to deliver it to the
          user agent.  A push service might retain values for a short duration
          after the TTL period to account for time accounting errors in
          processing.  For instance, distributing a push message within a server
          cluster might accrue errors due to clock variation, or processing and
          transit delays.
        </t>
        <t>
          A push service is not obligated to account for time spent by the
          application server in sending a push message to the push service, or
          delays incurred while sending a push message to the user agent.  An
          application server needs to account for transit delays in selecting a
          TTL header field value.
        </t>
        <t>
          Absence of the TTL header field is interpreted as equivalent to a zero
          value.  Push messages with a zero TTL indicate that storage is not
          needed and that the message can be dropped if the user agent isn't
          immediately available to receive the message.  Push messages with a
          zero TTL can be delivered very efficiently.
          <!-- But we need to determine if they can be acknowledged.  Decoupling
               of delivery and acknowledgment makes this tricky. -->
        </t>
        <t>
          A push service MAY choose to retain a push message for a shorter
          duration than that requested.  It indicates this by including a TTL
          header field in the response that includes the actual TTL.  This TTL
          value MUST be less than or equal to the value provided by the
          application server.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="monitor" title="Receiving Push Messages">
      <t>
        A user agent requests the delivery of new push messages by making a GET
        request to a push message subscription resource.  The push service does
        not respond to this request, it instead uses <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-http2">HTTP/2 server push</xref> to send the
        contents of push messages as they are sent by application servers.
      </t>
      <t>
        Each push message is pushed in response to a synthesized GET request.
        The GET request is made to the push message resource that was created by
        the push server when the application server requested message delivery.
        The response body is the entity body from the most recent request sent
        to the push resource.
      </t>

      <figure>
        <preamble>
          The following example request is made over HTTP/2.
        </preamble>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
HEADERS      [stream 7] +END_STREAM +END_HEADERS
  :method        = GET
  :path          = /s/LBhhw0OohO-Wl4Oi971UGsB7sdQGUibx
  :authority     = push.example.net
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <preamble>
          The push service permits the request to remain outstanding.  When a
          push message is sent by an application server, a server push is
          associated with the initial request.  The response includes the push
          message.
        </preamble>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
PUSH_PROMISE [stream 7; promised stream 4] +END_HEADERS
  :method        = GET
  :path          = /d/qDIYHNcfAIPP_5ITvURr-d6BGtYnTRnk
  :authority     = push.example.net

HEADERS      [stream 4] +END_HEADERS
  :status        = 200
  date           = Thu, 11 Dec 2014 23:56:56 GMT
  last-modified  = Thu, 11 Dec 2014 23:56:55 GMT
  cache-control  = private
  content-type   = text/plain;charset=utf8
  content-length = 36

DATA         [stream 4] +END_STREAM
  iChYuI3jMzt3ir20P8r_jgRR-dSuN182x7iB
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>
        A user agent can request the contents of the push message subscription
        resource immediately by including a <xref target="RFC7240">Prefer header
        field</xref> with a "wait" parameter set to "0".  In response to this
        request, the push service SHOULD return link references to the push and
        receipt subscribe resources, plus expiration information.  This request
        also triggers the delivery of all push messages that the push service
        has stored but not yet delivered.  The push service MUST generate a
        server push for all stored messages that have not yet been delivered.
      </t>
      <t>
        A 204 (No Content) status code with no associated server pushes
        indicates that no messages are presently available.
      </t>

      <section anchor="acknowledge_message"
               title="Acknowledging Push Messages">
        <t>
          To ensure that a push message is properly delivered to the user agent
          at least once, the user agent MUST acknowledge receipt of the message
          by performing a HTTP DELETE on the push message resource.
        </t>

        <figure>
          <artwork type="inline">
            <![CDATA[
DELETE /d/qDIYHNcfAIPP_5ITvURr-d6BGtYnTRnk HTTP/1.1
Host: push.example.net

]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>
          If the application has requested a delivery receipt, the push server
          MUST deliver a response to the application server monitoring the
          "receipt subscription" resource.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="receive_receipt" title="Receiving Push Message Receipts">
        <t>
          The application server requests the delivery of receipts from
          the push server by making a HTTP GET request to the "receipt
          subscription" resource. The push service does not respond to this
          request, it instead uses <xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-http2">HTTP/2
          server push</xref> to send push receipts when messages are
          acknowledged (<xref target="acknowledge_message"></xref>) by the user
          agent.
        </t>
        <t>
          Each receipt is pushed in response to a synthesized GET request.
          The GET request is made to the same "push message" resource that was
          created by the push server when the application server requested
          message delivery. A successful response includes a 410 (GONE) status
          code with no data.
        </t>

        <figure>
          <preamble>
            The following example request is made over HTTP/2.
          </preamble>
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
HEADERS      [stream 7] +END_STREAM +END_HEADERS
  :method        = GET
  :path          = /r/3ZtI4YVNBnUUZhuoChl6omUvG4ZM9mpN
  :authority     = push.example.net
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <figure>
          <preamble>
            The push service permits the request to remain outstanding.  When
            the user agent acknowledges the message, the push server pushes a
            delivery receipt to the application server. A 410 (Gone) status code
            confirms that the message was delivered and acknowledged.
          </preamble>
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
PUSH_PROMISE [stream 7; promised stream 4] +END_HEADERS
  :method        = GET
  :path          = /d/qDIYHNcfAIPP_5ITvURr-d6BGtYnTRnk
  :authority     = push.example.net

HEADERS      [stream 4] +END_STREAM
                        +END_HEADERS
  :status        = 410
  date           = Thu, 11 Dec 2014 23:56:56 GMT

]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="operational" title="Operational Considerations">
      <t>
        A push service is likely to have to maintain a very large number of open
        TCP connections.  Effective management of those connections can depend
        on being able to move connections between server instances.
      </t>

      <section anchor="load" title="Load Management">
        <t>
          A user agent MUST support the 307 (Temporary Redirect) status code
          <xref target="RFC7231"/>, which can be used by a push service to
          redistribute load at the time that a new subscription is requested.
        </t>
        <t>
          A server that wishes to redistribute load can do so using alternative
          services <xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-alt-svc"/>.  Alternative
          services allows for redistribution of load whilst maintaining the same
          URIs for various resources.  User agents can ensure a graceful
          transition by using the GOAWAY frame once it has established a
          replacement connection.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="storage" title="Push Message Expiration">
        <t>
          Storage of push messages based on the TTL header field comprises a
          potentially significant amount of storage for a push service.  A push
          service is not obligated to store messages indefinitely.  A push
          service is able to indicate how long it intends to retain a message to
          an application server using the TTL header field (see <xref
          target="ttl"/>).
        </t>
        <t>
          A user agent that does not actively monitor for push messages will not
          receive messages that expire during that interval.
        </t>
        <t>
          Push messages that are stored and not delivered to a user agent are
          delivered when the user agent recommences monitoring.  Stored push
          messages SHOULD include a Last-Modified header field (see Section 2.2
          of <xref target="RFC7232"/>) indicating when delivery was requested by
          an application server.
        </t>
        <t>
          A GET request to a "subscription" resource that has only expired
          messages results in response as though no push message were ever sent.
        </t>
        <t>
          Push services might need to limit the size and number of stored push
          messages to avoid overloading.  In addition to using the 413 (Payload
          Too Large) status code for too large push messages, a push service MAY
          expire push messages prior to any advertised expiration time.  A push
          service can reduce the impact push message retention by reducing the
          time-to-live of push messages. <!-- TODO note the need to advertise a
          lower bound on this reduction when we get to TTL guarantees -->
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="delete" title="Subscription Expiration">
        <t>
          In some cases, it may be necessary to terminate subscriptions so that
          they can be refreshed.
        </t>
        <t>
          A push service might choose to set a fixed expiration time.  If a
          resource has a known expiration time, expiration information is
          included in responses to requests that create the resource, or in
          requests that retrieve a representation of the resource.
        </t>
        <t>
          Expiration is indicated using either the Expires header field, or by
          setting a "max-age" parameter on a Cache-Control header field (see
          <xref target="RFC7234"/>).  The Cache-Control header field MUST also
          include the "private" directive.
        </t>
        <t>
          A push service can remove a subscription at any time. If a user agent
          has an outstanding request to a "subscription" resource (see <xref
          target="monitor"/>), this can be signaled by returning a 400-series
          status code, such as 410 (Gone).
        </t>
        <t>
          A user agent can request that a subscription be removed by sending a
          DELETE request to its private "subscription" URI.
        </t>
        <t>
          A push service MUST return a 400-series status code, such as 404 (Not
          Found) or 410 (Gone) if an application server attempts to send a push
          message to a removed or expired subscription.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Implications for Application Reliability">
        <t>
          A push server that does not support reliable delivery over
          intermittent network connections or failing applications on devices,
          forces the device to acknowledge receipt directly to the application
          server, incurring additional power drain in order to establish
          (usually secure) connections to the individual application servers.
        </t>
        <t>
          While reliability is not required for messages that expire in few
          seconds (e.g. an incoming call) or collapsible ones (e.g. the current
          number of unread emails), it is more important when messages contain
          information that is longer lasting, e.g. a command to update a
          configuration value, or the acknowledgement of a financial transaction
          or workflow step. In particular, in the case of power-constrained
          devices, it is preferable to transmit the actual information in the
          “pushed” message reliably, instead of forcing them to reconnect
          periodically to get the current state.
        </t>
        <t>
          The availability of push message delivery receipts in the protocol
          ensures that the application developer is not tempted to create
          alternative mechanisms for message delivery in case the push service
          fails to deliver a critical message. Setting up a polling mechanism or
          a backup messaging channel in order to compensate for these
          shortcomings negates almost all of the advantages a push service
          provides.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        This protocol MUST use <xref target="RFC2818">HTTP over TLS</xref>; this
        includes any communications between user agent and push service, plus
        communications between the application and the push service.  Thus, all
        URIs use the "https" scheme.  This provides confidentiality and
        integrity protection for subscriptions and push messages from external
        parties.
      </t>

      <section title="Confidentiality from Push Service Access">
        <t>
          The protection afforded by TLS does not protect content from the push
          service.  Without additional safeguards, a push service is able to see
          and modify the content of the messages.
        </t>
        <t>
          Applications are able to provide additional confidentiality, integrity
          or authentication mechanisms within the push message itself.  The
          application server sending the push message and the application on the
          user agent that receives it are frequently just different instances of
          the same application, so no standardized protocol is needed to
          establish a proper security context.  The process of providing the
          application server with subscription information provides a convenient
          medium for key agreement.
        </t>
        <t>
          <!-- Scrub references to specific API(s) -->
          The Web Push API codifies this practice by requiring that each push
          subscription created by the browser be bound to a browser generated
          encryption key.  Pushed messages are authenticated and decrypted by
          the browser before delivery to applications.  This scheme ensures that
          the push service is unable to examine the contents of push messages.
        </t>
        <t>
          The public key for a subscription ensures that applications using that
          subscription can identify messages from unknown sources and discard
          them.  This depends on the public key only being disclosed to entities
          that are authorized to send messages on the channel.  The push server
          does not require access to this public key.
        </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Privacy Considerations">
       <t>
         Push message confidentiality does not ensure that the identity of who
         is communicating and when they are communicating is protected.
         However, the amount of information that is exposed can be limited.
       </t>
       <t>
         The URIs provided for "push" resources MUST NOT provide any basis to
         correlate communications for a given user agent.  It MUST NOT be
         possible to correlate any two "push" URIs based solely on their
         contents.  This allows a user agent to control correlation across
         different applications, or over time.
       </t>
       <t>
         Similarly, the URIs provided by the push service to identify a push
         message MUST NOT provide any information that allows for correlation
         across subscriptions.  Push message URIs for the same subscription MAY
         contain information that would allow correlation with the associated
         subscription or other push messages for that subscription.
       </t>
       <t>
         User and device information MUST NOT be exposed through a "push" or
         push message URI.
       </t>
       <t>
         In addition, "push" URIs established by the same user agent or push
         message URIs for the same subscription MUST NOT include any information
         that allows them to be correlated with the user agent.
         <list style="hanging">
           <t hangText="Note:">
             This need not be perfect as long as the resulting anonymity set
             (see <xref target="RFC6973"/>, Section 6.1.1) is sufficiently
             large.  A "push" URI necessarily identifies a push service or
             a single server instance.  It is also possible that traffic
             analysis could be used to correlate subscriptions.
           </t>
         </list>
       </t>
       <t>
         A user agent MUST be able to create new subscriptions with new
         identifiers at any time.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section anchor="authorization" title="Authorization">
       <t>
         This protocol does not define how a push service establishes whether a
         user agent is permitted to create a subscription, or whether push
         messages can be delivered to the user agent.  A push service MAY choose
         to authorize requests based on any HTTP-compatible authorization method
         available, of which there are numerous options.  The authorization
         process and any associated credentials are expected to be configured in
         the user agent along with the URI for the "push service".
       </t>
       <t>
         Authorization is managed using "subscription", "push", "receipt
         subscription", and "receipt subscribe" capability URLs (see
         <xref target="CAP-URI"/>).  A capability URL grants access to a
         resource based solely on knowledge of the URL.
       </t>
       <t>
         Capability URLs are used for their "easy onward sharing" and "easy
         client API" properties. These make it possible to avoid relying on
         relationships between push services and application servers, with the
         protocols necessary to build and support those relationships.
        </t>
        <t>
         A "subscription", "push", "receipt subscription", "receipt subscribe",
         or push message URI acts as a bearer token.  Knowledge of a
         "subscription" URI implies authorization to either receive push
         messages or delete the subscription. Knowledge of a "push" URI implies
         authorization to send push messages.  Knowledge of a "receipt
         subscription" URI implies authorization to receive push receipts.
         Knowledge of a "receipt subscribe" URI implies authorization to create
         subscriptions for receipts. Knowledge of a push message URI allows for
         reading and acknowledging that specific message.
        </t>
        <t>
         Encoding a large amount of random entropy (at least 120 bits) in the
         path component ensures that it is difficult to successfully guess a
         valid capability URL.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Denial of Service Considerations">
       <t>
         Discarding unwanted messages at the user agent based on message
         authentication doesn't protect against a denial of service attack on
         the user agent.  Even a relatively small volume of push messages can
         cause battery-powered devices to exhaust power reserves.
       </t>
       <t>
         An application can limit where valid push messages can originate by
         limiting the distribution of "push" URIs to authorized entities.
         Ensuring that "push" URIs are hard to guess ensures that only
         application servers that have been given a "push" URI can use it.
       </t>
       <t>
         A malicious application with a valid "push" URI could use the greater
         resources of a push service to mount a denial of service attack on a
         user agent.  Push services SHOULD limit the rate at which push messages
         are sent to individual user agents.  A push service or user agent MAY
         <xref target="delete">terminate subscriptions</xref> that receive too
         many push messages.
       </t>
       <t>
         End-to-end confidentiality mechanisms, such as those in <xref
         target="API"/>, prevent an entity with a valid "subscription" URI from
         learning the contents of push messages.  Push messages that are not
         successfully authenticated will not be delivered by the API, but this
         can present a denial of service risk.
       </t>
       <t>
         Conversely, a push service is also able to deny service to user agents.
         Intentional failure to deliver messages is difficult to distinguish
         from faults, which might occur due to transient network errors,
         interruptions in user agent availability, or genuine service outages.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Logging Risks">
       <t>
         Server request logs can reveal subscription-related URIs. Acquiring a
         "subscription" URI enables the receipt of messages or deletion of the
         subscription. Acquiring a "push" URI permits the sending of push
         messages.  Logging could also reveal relationships between different
         subscription-related URIs for the same user agent.  Encrypted message
         contents are not revealed to the push service.
       </t>
       <t>
         Limitations on log retention and strong access control mechanisms can
         ensure that URIs are not learned by unauthorized entities.
       </t>
     </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        This protocol defines new HTTP header fields in <xref
        target="iana.header.fields"/>.  New link relation types are identified
        using the URNs defined in <xref target="iana.urns"/>.
      </t>

      <section anchor="iana.header.fields" title="Header Field Registrations">
        <t>
          HTTP header fields are registered within the "Message Headers"
          registry maintained at <eref
          target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/message-headers/"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          This document defines the following HTTP header fields, so their
          associated registry entries shall be added according to the permanent
          registrations below (see <xref target="RFC3864"/>):
        </t>
        <texttable align="left" suppress-title="true"
                   anchor="iana.header.registration.table">
          <ttcol>Header Field Name</ttcol>
          <ttcol>Protocol</ttcol>
          <ttcol>Status</ttcol>
          <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

          <c>TTL</c>
          <c>http</c>
          <c>standard</c>
          <c>
            <xref target="ttl"/>
          </c>
          <c>Push-Receipt</c>
          <c>http</c>
          <c>standard</c>
          <c>
            <xref target="request_receipt"/>
          </c>
        </texttable>
        <t>
          The change controller is: "IETF (iesg@ietf.org) - Internet
          Engineering Task Force".
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="iana.urns" title="Link Relation URNs">
        <t>
          This document registers URNs for use in identifying link relation
          types.  These are added to a new "Web Push Identifiers" registry
          according to the procedures in Section 4 of <xref target="RFC3553"/>;
          the corresponding "push" sub-namespace is entered in the "IETF URN
          Sub-namespace for Registered Protocol Parameter Identifiers"
          registry.
        </t>
        <t>
          The "Web Push Identifiers" registry operates under the <xref
          target="RFC5226">IETF Review policy</xref>.
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Registry name:">Web Push Identifiers</t>
            <t hangText="URN Prefix:">urn:ietf:params:push</t>
            <t hangText="Specification:">(this document)</t>
            <t hangText="Repository:">[Editor/IANA note: please include a link
            to the final registry location.]</t>
            <t hangText="Index value:">Values in this registry are URNs or URN
            prefixes that start with the prefix <spanx
            style="verb">urn:ietf:params:push</spanx>.  Each is registered
            independently.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          New registrations in the "Web Push Identifiers" are encouraged to
          include the following information:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="URN:">A complete URN or URN prefix.</t>
            <t hangText="Description:">A summary description.</t>
            <t hangText="Specification:">A reference to a specification
            describing the semantics of the URN or URN prefix.</t>
            <t hangText="Contact:">Email for the person or group making the
            registration.</t>
            <t hangText="Index value:">As described in <xref target="RFC3553"/>,
            URN prefixes that are registered include a description of how the
            URN is constructed.  This is not applicable for specific URNs.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          These values are entered as the initial content of the "Web Push
          Identifiers" registry.
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="URN:">urn:ietf:params:push:message</t>
            <t hangText="Description:">This link relation type is used to
            identify a resource for sending push messages.</t>
            <t hangText="Specification:">(this document)</t>
            <t hangText="Contact:">The Web Push WG (webpush@ietf.org)</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="URN:">urn:ietf:params:push:receipt:subscribe</t>
            <t hangText="Description:">
              This link relation type is used to identify a resource for
              creating new push message receipt subscriptions.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Specification:">(this document)</t>
            <t hangText="Contact:">The Web Push WG (webpush@ietf.org)</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
        Significant technical input to this document has been provided by Costin
        Manolache, Robert Sparks, Mark Nottingham, Matthew Kaufman and many
        others.
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title>
            Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels
          </title>
          <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>
            <address><email>sob@harvard.edu</email></address>
          </author>
          <date month="March" year="1997"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
      </reference>

     <reference anchor="RFC2818">
        <front>
          <title>
            HTTP Over TLS
          </title>
          <author initials="E." surname="Rescorla" fullname="Eric Rescorla"/>
          <date month="May" year="2000"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2818"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3553">
        <front>
          <title>An IETF URN Sub-namespace for Registered Protocol Parameters</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Mealling" fullname="M. Mealling">
          <organization /></author>
          <author initials="L." surname="Masinter" fullname="L. Masinter">
          <organization /></author>
          <author initials="T." surname="Hardie" fullname="T. Hardie">
          <organization /></author>
          <author initials="G." surname="Klyne" fullname="G. Klyne">
          <organization /></author>
          <date year="2003" month="June" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="73" />
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3553" />
        <format type="TXT" octets="14815" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3553.txt" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3864">
        <front>
          <title>Registration Procedures for Message Header Fields</title>
          <author initials="G." surname="Klyne" fullname="G. Klyne">
          <organization /></author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="M. Nottingham">
          <organization /></author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Mogul" fullname="J. Mogul">
          <organization /></author>
          <date year="2004" month="September" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="90" />
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3864" />
        <format type="TXT" octets="36231" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3864.txt" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5226">
        <front>
          <title>Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs</title>
          <author initials="T." surname="Narten" fullname="T. Narten">
          <organization /></author>
          <author initials="H." surname="Alvestrand" fullname="H. Alvestrand">
          <organization /></author>
          <date year="2008" month="May" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="26" />
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5226" />
        <format type="TXT" octets="66160" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5226.txt" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5988">
        <front>
          <title>Web Linking</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="M. Nottingham">
          <organization /></author>
          <date year="2010" month="October" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5988" />
        <format type="TXT" octets="46834" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5988.txt" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC7230">
        <front>
          <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Message Syntax and Routing</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="R. Fielding">
          <organization /></author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Reschke" fullname="J. Reschke">
          <organization /></author>
          <date year="2014" month="June" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7230" />
        <format type="TXT" octets="205947" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc7230.txt" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC7231">
        <front>
          <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Semantics and Content</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="R. Fielding">
          <organization /></author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Reschke" fullname="J. Reschke">
          <organization /></author>
          <date year="2014" month="June" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7231" />
        <format type="TXT" octets="235053" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc7231.txt" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC7232">
        <front>
          <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Conditional Requests</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="R. Fielding">
          <organization /></author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Reschke" fullname="J. Reschke">
          <organization /></author>
          <date year="2014" month="June" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7232" />
        <format type="TXT" octets="56696" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc7232.txt" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC7234">
        <front>
          <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Caching</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="R. Fielding">
          <organization /></author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="M. Nottingham">
          <organization /></author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Reschke" fullname="J. Reschke">
          <organization /></author>
          <date year="2014" month="June" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7234" />
        <format type="TXT" octets="90647" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc7234.txt" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC7240">
        <front>
          <title>Prefer Header for HTTP</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Snell" fullname="J. Snell">
          <organization /></author>
          <date year="2014" month="June" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7240" />
        <format type="TXT" octets="32796" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc7240.txt" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-httpbis-http2">
        <front>
          <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol version 2</title>
          <author initials="M" surname="Belshe" fullname="Mike Belshe">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials="R" surname="Peon" fullname="Roberto Peon">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials="M" surname="Thomson" fullname="Martin Thomson">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="February" day="10" year="2015" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-httpbis-http2-17" />
        <format type="TXT"
                target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-httpbis-http2-17.txt" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-httpbis-alt-svc">
        <front>
          <title>HTTP Alternative Services</title>
          <author initials="M" surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials="P" surname="McManus" fullname="Patrick McManus">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials="J" surname="Reschke" fullname="Julian Reschke">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="February" day="5" year="2015" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-httpbis-alt-svc-06" />
        <format type="TXT"
                target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-httpbis-alt-svc-06.txt" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="CAP-URI" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/capability-urls/">
        <front>
          <title>Good Practices for Capability URLs</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Tennison" fullname="Jeni Tennison"/>
          <date month="February" year="2014"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="FPWD" value="capability-urls"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="API" target="https://w3c.github.io/push-api/">
        <front>
          <title>Web Push API</title>
          <author initials="B." surname="Sullivan" fullname="Bryan Sullivan"/>
          <author initials="E." surname="Fullea" fullname="Eduardo Fullea"/>
          <author initials="M." surname="van Ouwerkerk" fullname="Michael van Ouwerkerk"/>
          <date month="February" year="2015" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ED" value="push-api" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC6973">
        <front>
          <title>Privacy Considerations for Internet Protocols</title>
          <author initials="A." surname="Cooper" fullname="A. Cooper">
          <organization /></author>
          <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="H. Tschofenig">
          <organization /></author>
          <author initials="B." surname="Aboba" fullname="B. Aboba">
          <organization /></author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Peterson" fullname="J. Peterson">
          <organization /></author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Morris" fullname="J. Morris">
          <organization /></author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Hansen" fullname="M. Hansen">
          <organization /></author>
          <author initials="R." surname="Smith" fullname="R. Smith">
          <organization /></author>
          <date year="2013" month="July" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6973" />
        <format type="TXT" octets="89198" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6973.txt" />
      </reference>

    </references>

    <!--
        <section title="Change Log">
        <t>[[The RFC Editor is requested to remove this section at publication.]]</t>
        <t>Changes since -0-1:
        <list style="symbols">
        <t>Document created.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        </section>
    -->
  </back>
</rfc>
